So I am a pediatric cancer doctor
أنا طبيب سرطان أطفال
and stem-cell researcher at Stanford University
وباحث في الخلايا الجذعية في جامعة ستانفورد
where my clinical focus has been bone marrow transplantation.
حيث كان تركيزي السريري على زراعة نخاع العظام
Now, inspired by Jill Bolte Taylor last year,
الآن، ملهما من حديث جل بولت تيلور العام الماضي
I didn't bring a human brain,
لم أحضر دماغا بشرية
but I did bring a liter of bone marrow.
ولكنني أحضرت لتراً من نخاع العظام
And bone marrow is actually what we use
ونخاع العظام هو ما نستخدمه
to save the lives of tens of thousands of patients,
لإنقاذ حياة عشرات الآلاف من المرضى
most of whom have advanced malignancies like leukemia and lymphoma
معظمهم في مراحل متقدمة من السرطان مثل الدم واللمفاوية
and some other diseases.
وبعض الأمراض الأخرى
So, a few years ago, I'm doing my transplant fellowship at Stanford.
إذا، منذ بضع سنوات، كنت أقوم بزمالتي في الزراعة في ستانفورد
I'm in the operating room. We have Bob here,
أنا في غرفة العمليات. لدينا بوب هنا
who is a volunteer donor.
وهو متبرع متطوع
We're sending his marrow across the country to save the life
نرسل نخاعه عبر البلاد لإنقاذ حياة
of a child with leukemia.
طفل مصاب بسرطان الدم
So actually how do we harvest this bone marrow?
فكيف إذا نحصد هذا النخاع؟
Well we have a whole O.R. team, general anesthesia, nurses,
لدينا فريق عمليات متكامل، تخدير كامل، ممرضات
and another doctor across from me.
وطبيب آخر يقابلني
Bob's on the table, and we take this sort of small needle,
بوب على الطاولة، ونأخذ إبرة صغيرة
you know, not too big.
كما تعلمون، ليست كبيرة جدا
And the way we do this is we basically
والطريقة التي نقوم بذلك أننا
place this through the soft tissue,
نمررها عبر الأنسجة اللينة
and kind of punch it into the hard bone,
ونكبسها نوعا ما في العظم الصلب
into the tuchus -- that's a technical term --
إلى التوتشس -- ذلك مصطلح فني -ـ
and aspirate about 10 mls of bone marrow out,
وننضح حوالي 10 ملل من نخاع العظم
each time, with a syringe.
كل مرة، بمحقن
And hand it off to the nurse. She squirts it into a tin.
ونسلمها للممرضة. تسكبها في صفيحة
Hands it back to me. And we do that again and again.
تسلمها لي مجددا. ونقوم بذلك عدة مرات
About 200 times usually.
عادة حوالي 200 مرة
And by the end of this my arm is sore, I've got a callus on my hand,
وفي نهاية ذلك تؤلمني ذراعي، ولدي دعوات في يدي
let alone Bob,
هذا غير بوب
whose rear end looks something more like this,
الذي تبدو مؤخرته شيئا كهذا
like Swiss cheese.
مثل الجبن السويسري
So I'm thinking, you know, this procedure hasn't changed in about 40 years.
ففكرت، هذه العملية لم تتغير منذ ما يقرب من 40 عام
And there is probably a better way to do this.
ولابد أن هناك طريقة أفضل للقيام بذلك
So I thought of a minimally invasive approach,
ففكرت في طريقة للحد من الألم
and a new device that we call the Marrow Miner.
وجهاز جديد نسميه حاصد النخاع
This is it.
هو هذا
And the Marrow Miner, the way it works is shown here.
وحاصد النخاع، يعمل كما هو موضح هنا
Our standard see-through patient.
مريضنا الشفاف القياسي
Instead of entering the bone dozens of times,
عوضا عن دخول العظم عدة مرات
we enter just once, into the front of the hip or the back of the hip.
ندخل فقط مرة، في مقدمة الحوض أو مؤخرة الحوض
And we have a flexible, powered catheter
ولدينا مقسطر قوي مرن
with a special wire loop tip that stays inside the crunchy part of the marrow
مع حلقة سلكية خاصة تبقى في المنطقة المفتتة من النخاع
and follows the contours of the hip, as it moves around.
وتتبع خارطة الحوض ، في حركتها
So it enables you to very rapidly aspirate,
فتمكننا من النضح بسرعة كبيرة
or suck out, rich bone marrow very quickly through one hole.
أو شفط، نخاع عظمي غني جدا بسرعة كبيرة من ثقب واحد
We can do multiple passes through that same entry.
يمكننا عمل عدة تمريرات من نفس المدخل
No robots required.
دون الحاجة إلى أي روبوتات
And, so, very quickly, Bob can just get one puncture, local anesthesia,
وبذلك، وبسرعة كبيرة، يمكن لبوب أن يحصل على ثقب واحد، تخدير موضعي
and do this harvest as an outpatient.
وعمل هذا الحصد كمريض خارجي
So I did a few prototypes. I got a small little grant at Stanford.
فقمت بعدة نماذج. حصلت على منحة صغيرة من ستانفورد
And played around with this a little bit.
ولعبت بهذا بعض الشيء
And our team members developed this technology.
وأنتج أعضاء فريقنا هذه التقنية
And eventually we got two large animals, and pig studies.
وحصلنا في نهاية المطاف على حيوانين للدراسة
And we found, to our surprise, that we not only got bone marrow out,
ووجدنا، لدهشتنا، أننا لن نحصل على نخاع عظمي فحسب
but we got 10 times the stem cell activity
ولكننا حصلنا على 10 أضعاف النشاط الخلوي
in the marrow from the Marrow Miner, compared to the normal device.
في النخاع من حاصد النخاع، بالمقارنة بالأداة التقليدية
This device was just FDA approved in the last year.
لقد تم اعتماد هذه الأداة العام الماضي
Here is a live patient. You can see it following the flexible curves around.
هذا مريض حقيقي. يمكنكم رؤيتها تتبع المنحنى بسلاسة
There will be two passes here, in the same patient, from the same hole.
سيكون هناك تكرارين، في نفس المريض، من نفس الثقب
This was done under local anesthesia, as an outpatient.
لقد تم هذا تحت تأثير بنج موضعي، كمريض عيادة خارجية
And we got, again, about three to six times more stem cells
وحصلنا، مرة أخرى، على ثلاث إلى ست أضعاف الخلايا الجذعية
than the standard approach done on the same patient.
من الطريقة التقليدية على نفس المريض
So why should you care? Bone marrow is a very rich source of adult stem cells.
فلماذا نهتم؟ نخاع العظام مصدر غني جدا للخلايا الجذعية البالغة
You all know about embryonic stem cells.
جميعكم سمع عن الخلايا الجذعية الجنينية
They've got great potential but haven't yet entered clinical trials.
لديها مستقبل باهر ولكنها لم تدخل في التجارب السريرية
Adult stem cells are throughout our body,
الخلايا الجذعية البالغة تنتشر في أجسادنا
including the blood-forming stem cells in our bone marrow,
بما في ذلك الخلايا الجذعية المكونة للدماء في نخاع العظم
which we've been using as a form of stem-cell therapy
والتي نستخدمها كنوع من العلاج بالخلايا الجذعية
for over 40 years.
منذ أكثر من 40 عام
In the last decade there's been an explosion of use
في العقد الماضي حدث انفجار في استخدام
of bone marrow stem cells to treat the patient's other diseases
الخلايا الجذعية من نخاع العظام لعلاج أمراض أخرى
such as heart disease, vascular disease,
مثل أمراض القلب، أمراض الشرايين
orthopedics, tissue engineering,
العظام، وهندسة الأنسجة
even in neurology to treat Parkinson's
حتى في الأعصاب لعلاج باركنسون
and diabetes.
والسكري
We've just come out, we're commercializing, this year,
لقد خرجنا للتو، هذا العام، بالنسخة التجارية
generation 2.0 of the Marrow Miner.
الجيل الثاني من حاصد النخاع
The hope is that this gets more stem cells out,
الأمل أنها تحصل على عدد أكبر من الخلايا الجذعية
which translates to better outcomes.
والتي تترجم إلى نتائج أفضل
It may encourage more people to sign up to be
قد تشجع أشخاص أكثر ليسجلوا ليصبحوا
potential live-saving bone marrow donors.
متبرعين بنخاع العظام وينقذوا الأرواح
It may even enable you to bank
وقد تمكنك من تخزين
your own marrow stem cells, when you're younger and healthier,
خلاياك الجذعية النخاعية، في شبابك وصحتك
to use in the future should you need it.
لتستخدمها في المستقبل، لو احتجت إليها
And ultimately -- and here's a picture of our
وأخيرا -- وهذه صورة لكم للناجين
bone marrow transplant survivors,
من عمليات زراعة نخاع العظام
who come together for a reunion each year at Stanford.
الذين يجتمعون سنويا في ستانفورد
Hopefully this technology will let us
آملين أن تمكننا هذه التقنية
have more of these survivors in the future.
من زيادة عدد هؤلاء الناجين في المستقبل
Thanks.
شكرا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)